Finding Aid for H. J. (Henry Jacob) Gomberg Papers 1941-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
H. J. (Henry Jacob) Gomberg Papers 1941-1995, 1955-1980
Gomberg, H. J. (Henry Jacob), 1918-
3 linear feet
University of Michigan professor of nuclear engineering; files relating to his Central American peace interests and to the peaceful uses of nuclear energy; also class notes, personal / biographical information, and visual material.
93198 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mrs. Edith Gomberg (donor 8420 ) beginning first in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
Henry J. Gomberg was born in New York City on April 16, 1918. He began his higher education at the City College of New York before transferring to the University of Michigan. While at Michigan, Gomberg earned his B.S.E. (1941), M.S.E. (1943), and Ph.D. (1951) in electrical engineering.
In 1941, Gomberg began his teaching career at the University of Michigan while working on his Ph.D.; he was appointed as a Teaching Fellow from 1941 to 1942. He served as a member of the faculty of nuclear engineering from 1946 to 1961. In 1952, he received the University's prestigious Henry Russel Award which honors faculty who show great promise for the future. From 1958 to 1961, he served as chairman of the Nuclear Engineering Department. Gomberg was also the director of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, which was dedicated to the memory of university students who had died in World War II. The project was created to explore the peaceful uses of nuclear energy.
Gomberg received a number of awards and honors and likewise held many positions throughout his career. In addition to the above, he served as president and chief executive officer of KMS Fusion and KMS Industries in Ann Arbor, Michigan, from 1971 to 1980. He was also the founder of Ann Arbor Nuclear Inc. His interests were varied but are best represented by his research in nuclear energy and his involvement in the Central American Coalition for Peace, which aimed to stop guerrilla warfare and improve relations between Central American nations and the United States.
Henry J. Gomberg died on April 8, 1995 at the age of seventy six.
Nuclear engineer Henry Jacob Gomberg was a faculty member at the University of Michigan from 1946 to 1961 as well as director of the Puerto Rico Nuclear Center. He later worked for nuclear engineering business in the private sector. The Gomberg collection mainly contains materials from his numerous professional ventures in the nuclear energy field. It includes correspondence, personal notes, photographs, publications, and reports.
The Henry J. Gomberg collection, covering the period of 1941 to 1995, is divided into nine series: Central American Peace Interests; Class Notes; International Cooperation Administration (ICA); KMS Industries; Peaceful Uses of Nuclear Energy; Personal / Biographical; Puerto Rico; University of Michigan, and Visual Material.
Subjects:
Central America--Social conditions--1979-; Gomberg, H. J. (Henry Jacob), 1918-1995; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Gomberg, H. J. (Henry Jacob), 1918-1995; Nuclear power plants.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Central American Peace Interests
  Ordered chronologically, the Central American Peace Interests series, 1986-1988 (0.1 linear feet) is divided into two folders and contains many pamphlets, flyers, membership directories, and issue statements. This material aptly reflects Gomberg's fervent wish for peace in Central America and spans the time period between 1986 and 1988.
  - Central America, May 1986-September, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Central America, October 1987-May, 1988 (Box 1)
- Class Notes
  The Class Notes series, 1941-1957 (0.6 linear feet) contains notes from classes taken and notes from classes taught. The course subjects focus on the obvious topics concerning engineering, such as "Modern Operational Mathematics" and "Quantum Mechanics."
  - Courses Taken 1941-1947
    - Untitled (3), 194? (Box 1)
    - Garsons Report, 194? (Box 1)
    - Modern Operational Mathematics and Problems, 194? (Box 1)
    - Quantum Mechanics, 194? (Box 1)
    - High Vacuum Tubes and Gaseous Conduction 1941 (Box 1)
    - Physics--E & M Theory 1946 (Box 1)
    - Elementary Particles 1947 (Box 1)
  - Courses Taught 1957
    - Nuclear Engineering 1957 (Box 1)
- Peaceful Uses of Nuclear Energy
  The series Peaceful Uses of Nuclear Energy, 1949-1995 (0.4 linear feet) contains several folders on various topics of interest to Gomberg. Included is information on the Ann Arbor Nuclear Free Zone proposal, the Oak Ridge Radioisotope Conference, and the Phoenix Project. There are also two folders of miscellaneous nuclear interests which contain newspaper clippings, a presentation which Gomberg attended and annotated, and rough drafts of his own editorials/articles. Folders in this series are arranged alphabetically.
  - Ann Arbor Nuclear Free Zone 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1940-1961 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Oak Ridge Radioisotope Conference 1963 (Box 1)
  - Penetron Inc. 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Phoenix Project 1949-1961 (Box 1)
  - Presentation 1961-1962 (Box 1)
- Personal/Biographical
  The Personal / Biographical series, 1941-1988 (0.2 linear feet) consists of a variety of mixed materials, ordered chronologically. Personal correspondence, mementos, newspaper clippings, the notification of his appointment as a teaching fellow, and two plaques honoring patents are all included in this series. Regarding Gombergs' family history, some papers and correspondence in this series document his genealogy. Also included is a bound volume of Gomberg's scientific articles from 1946 to 1971. It was compiled in honor of his sixtieth birthday on April 16, 1978.
  - 1941-1988 (Box 2)
  - 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Bound set of publications 1946-1971 (Box 2)
- International Cooperation Administration (ICA)
  Ordered topically, the International Cooperation Administration (ICA) series, 1955-1961 (0.5 linear feet) is divided into ten folders and contains materials in the formats of personal correspondence, photographs, publications, and official reports. This material reflects Gomberg's involvement in the international community in regards to peaceful uses of nuclear energy. A major component of this series is background on the individual countries that Gomberg visited during this time period as well as a 1955 United Nations Conference on atomic energy in which he was an invited delegate.
  - Correspondence 1959 (Box 2)
  - Countries
    - Ecuador 1958, undated (Box 2)
    - Greece 1959-1961, undated (Box 2)
    - Japan 1955-1959, undated (Box 2)
    - Korea, (includes photographs)1955-1960 and undated (Box 2)
    - Latin America 1956, undated (Box 2)
    - USSR 1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Geneva (United Nations Conference) 1955 (Box 2)
  - Reports 1957-1959, undated (Box 2)
- KMS
  KMS Industries, 1947-1994 (bulk dates 1971-1984) (0.5 linear feet) represents a major portion of Gomberg's post University of Michigan career. There are a few items from a much earlier time period, 1947, which provide the background for a scientific experiment that was utilized much later during his career at KMS Industries. Keeve M. Siegel, a colleague of Gomberg, founded KMS Industries in Ann Arbor. The materials in the ten folders are arranged topically spanning his initial involvement with the corporation, his career as president, and subsequent resignation in 1980. This series houses the one audio artifact of the collection, a cassette tape which documents a KMS business transaction regarding financial solvency. Additionally, there is a physical artifact (medallion) that commemorates the tenth anniversary of achieving nuclear fusion by KMS corporation.
  - Ann Arbor Nuclear, Inc. 1982-1994 (Box 2)
  - Artifact (Fusion Anniversary Medallion) 1984 (Box 2)
  - Audio Cassette (Discussion with Schroeder Company) 1977 (Box 2)
  - Background 1971-1987 (Box 2)
  - Laser Fusion 1972-1979, undated (Box 2)
  - Launcher Project 1947-1974, undated (Box 2)
  - Patent 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Personal Notes 1979-1981, undated (Box 3)
  - Radsyn 1973-1986 (Box 3)
  - Resignation and Background 1970-1984, undated (Box 3)
  - Stock Information 1971-1991 (Box 3)
- Puerto Rico
  Puerto Rico, 1958-1988 (0.5 linear feet) consists of many formats of materials such as correspondence, newspaper clippings, personal notes, and publications. The wide array of materials in the six folders document Gomberg's involvement with the Puerto Rico Nuclear Center as well as the University of Puerto Rico. He served as director of the Puerto Rico Nuclear Center in the 1960s. This series also includes correspondence with Nobel Peace Prize winner Glenn Seaborg in his role with the United States Atomic Energy Commission.
  - Correspondence 1966-1988 (Box 3)
  - Desalination 1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Puerto Rico Nuclear Center 1961-1972, undated (Box 3)
  - Reports 1958-1969 (Box 3)
  - University of Puerto Rico 1970-1971, undated (Box 3)
- University of Michigan
  University of Michigan, undated, (0.3 linear feet) is comprised of notes on experiments and projects in his nuclear engineering field.
  - Experiments, Notes, and Projects undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series, 1941-1992 (0.3 linear feet) consists of several photographs taken between 1941 and 1992. The majority of the photographs are of Gomberg, but also included are images of nuclear facilities as well as a reception in Gomberg's honor. In addition to the photographs, two videotapes are housed in this series, one documenting Gomberg's memorial service in April 1995 (VHS), while the other is a videotaped interview with Gomberg concerning nuclear energy, circa 1981 (U-matic).
  - Photographs 1941-1992 (Box 3)
  - Videotape: Kelly at Night Program: "Is Nuclear Necessary?" 1981, U-matic (Box 3)
  - Videotape: Memorial Henry Gomberg 1995, VHS (Box 3)